all right welcome to the solution
raising on shelter
so this is specifically shelter did i
call it shelter housing like not the
community aspect of it but the physical
structure that keeps you safe from
elements
so that's a good enough definition so
like all solution reasons let's first
talk for 50 or roughly 15 minutes
on what shelter currently looks like for
us for everybody else in the world
and then switch over to what we would
love it to look like
in our ideal vision of the future
however are the future you need that to
be
and then the last half we'll discuss
what we could do
to empower people in the area of shelter
if we had 10 000 people and a hundred
thousand dollars
so who would like to start
i can start no one else like to
um this is hard because shelter's
expensive
like like in order to have shelter
you need the physical thing
the roof and the walls and the doors and
the windows hopefully
and the space to put it and of course in
a city those are very intimately tied
together
you need to buy the land and you build
and it's supposed to last for
50 100 years just which is no longer the
case
they build them to last you know 10
maybe 20 years i know in my neighborhood
there's construction on both sides of me
right now because every time a house
sells it's being torn down in a new
one's being built
because the property taxes are way too
high here to um
pay for your land pay your property
taxes and not have a million dollar home
on it
like the house i live in is a million
dollar home it's not a million-dollar
home the property it's sitting on is a
million dollars
so that is a bit of my shelter and i'm
looking to
like rent is astronomically expensive
even
the newer like tiny houses if you buy
them and don't build them yourself
are still in the price range of what a
mortgage used to be a generation ago
like a mortgage with a house and a yard
and so
and you don't have the land to put it on
like that doesn't include the tiny house
it includes the tiny house not the rest
of it
so um this is a topic that i haven't
tackled we haven't tackled yet because i
don't know
what a solution is and
that's why it excites me also talk about
it because i don't know what's gonna i
have no idea what's gonna come up in the
third section
sometimes i have an inkling how about
you guys what is your shelter situation
or what how do you see shelter right now
well it's funny you mentioned cities
because i think i think that's an
important
i think that's an important um
distinction to be drawing right because
i mean cities have a lot of things that
attract people to them right there's
culture
and there's excitement and there's you
know movies and theaters and sports
teams and
lots of jobs and all of that kind of
thing but but
you know cities would grow forever given
all of those attractions but one of the
things that holds back the growth of the
city is limitation
on exactly that on space and thus
housing
um so yeah while a city is popular given
that there is a finite amount of land
you can build houses on while the city's
popular is attracting people the only
way that that can be expressed is
elevation of house prices right because
the demand for
the people you know the demand for of
for housing from people coming in cannot
be met by
new housing being produced so the
inevitable consequence of that
is an increase in prices so but but that
but that
has knock-on effects right i mean what
what i've done with my life is i sold up
in the uk and i bought in spain which is
much cheaper right and so i was able to
get a lot more for my money have a chunk
of cash aside and so i don't have people
but my point is if lots of people do
that then the prices of properties in
rural spain start to go up which means
that the locals can no longer afford to
buy property here anymore you know what
i mean and so the
the spill out effect of people
from cities who can't afford to buy in
the cities and they move out to rural
areas because it's cheaper make the
rural areas more expensive people that
live there can't live there anymore and
so on and so on and so on and so on and
so on right so it's a
it's a non-stop ripple effect um that
goes on and it goes on you know
as i said it goes right across the world
you know it's not it's not contained by
national
borders so yeah it's a it's it's
a massive problem while people continue
to flow into cities
and the cities can't keep up with the
demand for housing and the prices in
cities go up to the point where people
move out of the cities to find but there
but then that
yeah it's it's well money is connected
to housing while you have to have money
in order to get housing there are always
going to be lots and lots of people who
can't get housing it's as simple as that
well for me shelter has been um a
personal
thing um jubilee and i think carrie
know that i i drove across canada my um
my youngest daughter
gave birth on may may 7th i think
and so when the pandemic started
i wasn't sure how far society was going
to degrade so
i uh packed up everything i needed and
gave up my apartment here in regina and
drove 32 hours
with one stop to ottawa
and so i lived with my
my eldest daughter to self to isolate
quarantine for 14 days
that was my youngest daughter for a
month and a half
and then with my uh siblings in montreal
for a little bit
and then my friends in trenton for a
little bit
and then friends here in regina
for another two weeks another friend for
another two weeks and finally an
apartment
so for me shelter personally is
without it it's very unsettling
much more unsettling than i i would have
thought like it
disrupts my my thought pattern you know
it's just
so i i understand how it could be that
for somebody else
and and personally in the midst of that
i'm
i'm downsizing i gave away my king-size
bed i loved it when i first
got a king-sized bed like 35 years ago
couldn't wait to get rid of it after
traipsing across the country and um
putting my stuff in storage
so now i'm of the mindset i want to
to minimize as much as i can and have
something as small as possible
and it's that's an unsettling thing
because a lot of my friends have big
places
sea-doos boats you know they're they're
hard workers
and i don't want to judge them i i was
just on a sea doo uh this weekend i
used to have one and i i loved it but
then i thought having that and the big
cottage on the lake
versus how it feels when i'm sitting
there something
feeling not right versus when i'm
i'm i've got what i need i feel safe i
feel
settled and that feeling inside if i had
to compare the two
i would go towards a minimal i think i'm
going to end up in a tiny house that's
what it feels like
i was just going to mention tiny houses
too if you hadn't already heard them and
also there's a documentary on netflix
i think it's on netflix called
minimalism it might be on youtube as
well worth a look if you haven't seen it
you'll find it really interesting if you
haven't seen it
yeah it feels it feels like that's where
i'm headed i'm i'm more and more
[Music]
there's less and less dissonance in me
the more i'm headed that way
that's what i'm feeling
all right i can go um
okay so first i'm just gonna uh name
drop
uh this book there so i'm from the
united states
so my shelter perceptions uh are
partially
uh you know covered in
what i notice here in the united states
um there is an awesome book
called building suburbia that
uh goes into like a 200 year history of
like how we've built out suburbs and why
cities are the way that they are and
things like that and like the problems
with them and some of the good things i
guess what i'm going to do
is just like list a couple problems that
i notice
and then in the second half maybe i'll
just talk about one of them but i
noticed a lot of different things
our shelter is related to economics
i think that as long as we're looking at
shelter as an investment rather than
a place where people actually live
um we've got a big problem um
because we're you know it it's entangled
with
uh making money off of
off of property but human beings have to
live there and
it's it's very complicated i do think we
have a tension between
um like we've got these problems yet
at the same time um with where we've
come
in the last hundred years with building
materials and safety
like in some ways it's better than it's
ever been
but in other ways it's hurting people
economically so some other parts of this
list
i think we overuse some buildings as
shelter
that's like large homes empty nesters
with four bedroom houses and they just
live in the one and then they've got
extra bedrooms that aren't being used so
there's like
homes that aren't being utilized they're
not filled up and then you've got
families like with large families that
are in like a two-bedroom apartment
and so there's an exchange that's not
being made
i think that we misuse other properties
um i think about churches that like can
pack a whole bunch of people in
yet you know should part of the building
be used as a homeless shelter or
something like that we're misusing uh
property i think that the
big landowners the elite landowners are
not on the side
of the people um and i don't think we
use shelter as a tool
for flourishing there's like cultural
perceptions
um these tiny houses were mentioned i
know someone that's doing van life
like there's a lot of flourishing from
van life
like they get to move around the country
all the time this awesome sense of
traveling and like there's some
flourishing
that is happening it's like holding up
certain cultural perceptions
is not helpful for like the primates
that we are um and
it's related to depression and other
things like that so there's like a lot
laundry list of stuff that's all i got
okay well aid and edinburgh are talking
about shelter and some of the big hotels
because they were lying empty
um all the homeless people were kind of
pulling there
but they've all been thrown out again
now because they're open enough so i
don't know what's happened
to most of them um all the air b and b
there's legislation being passed now
because like loads of people have bought
air b and b's uh
places houses to rent out for their
being being short term and there's
hundreds and hundreds of them
and so that's put the rent up at the
rental market
um there is a container
site with tiny houses and stuff like
that but it's in the middle of nowhere
um so and there's already any bus
services so i was supposed to get into
town for the job so
um shelter you well as i said you
absolutely need it because without it
you just kind of lost really
and every day is just trying to figure
out you know trying not to get your leg
kicked in
because you've got nowhere to stay or be
molested or whatever
um property market is expensive
rental market is expensive we're all a
bit fucked really
um so that's that's about all of i can i
can say to that because obviously it's
different in different countries like
people who would homeless here might be
better off than someone who's in a
refugee camp
i don't know you know what i mean
because i've not been there so i can't
tell
and but shelter's going to be it means
the same to everyone you need a roof
over your dad for your own
well-being you know as i said you need
to be able to go to sleep safely knowing
no one's going to come in and kick your
head in and um
to be able to plan because you can't
plan if you've got no shelter you can't
plan a life
you can't because you don't know where
you're going to be from day to day so um
i've got personal experience of that so
so yeah so
that's that's about it really
all right yeah i just want to i just
want to pick up a little bit on what
daniel was saying and just just amplify
it really i mean the
the um amount of rent seeking that goes
on
in jan i don't just mean you know
demanding but you know the the
um the appreciation of the asset and the
income from the assets simultaneously
right if you are if you are an owner of
a
block of flats for example right you've
got an asset which is becoming worth
more money all the time and you're
generating a very nice income flow and
you're doing fuck all right you're not
doing absolutely not doing
especially if you're a shit landlord not
even maintaining the building you're
doing fuck all for that right
and so you are just you are literally a
parasite on society
sucking the lifeblood out of it right
and providing absolutely nothing in
return it's not like you built the thing
you know what i mean we did with the
sweat of your own brow you know what i
mean
uh so all you did was borrow money buy
the building pay off the loan with the
rent from the poor people in you but you
know what i mean it's
it's it's a it's a cancer in the society
as a whole so yeah i just wanted to
amplify that point
yeah i don't i don't know how i feel
about my landlord because there's no way
i would be able to afford to live in
vancouver and own it
at the same time if people weren't
buying um especially
you know people who don't have canadian
citizenship they're not living here
their kids aren't going to school here
and they're buying it as an investment
and no one's living in it
if that didn't exist maybe i could
afford to
to rent would be cheaper for sure and so
i could afford like if the city owned it
or we owned it collectively i don't know
and so i don't i'm glad i have my
landlord needs a fairly good landlord
and yet i agree like i agree that
that there's not that they're parasites
because i think like anything in game a
they're doing the best they can and some
of them you know like they have a home
they're they're figuring how to make
their ends meet they have
another home so they can rent it out and
they see it as it like employing someone
like it's
they're getting and they are taking a
risk however
we're about to see that risk come to
fruition during cobit 19 when people
can't pay rent and then they can't pay
rent and they can't pay their mortgages
um
if anyone has anything else to add
during this section before we switch to
what it could be
i mean i think you're right let some
landlords do the best that or many
landlords even i mean i don't know what
the numbers are it's irrelevant but many
are doing the best they can i agree with
you but they are
trapped in this thing where they have a
loan on a property which they have to
repay and they have to feed their
families and so
the fact is with the best will in the
world they are they are they
they are required to make a profit on
the rent from the building right and if
that requirement to make profit from
just people needing somewhere to live
right it's not like this is a luxury
thing right this is people need
somewhere to live
and that is being made profits from if
the demand for profit wasn't there you
could as
as you started saying right you could
collectively own the building with the
other people living there pay the
mortgage collectively and it would have
to cost you less than the rent that you
are currently paying right because the
rate you're paying has to include
a profit for the landlord right so
that's a piece of it that's no longer
true
not here anyway maybe not right now but
you know what i mean no
i mean for for like a decade when my
parents bought a house the one house
they owned we bought it because
mortgages were cheaper than rent
there is actually a risk because people
are like real estate goes up and up and
up and up so because that's that's like
in our head
you can like you can rent out your place
for 2 000 let's say
the bank your mortgage might absolutely
be 2 500 3 000
and you are paying the difference and so
if you're not getting that rent you have
to cover 3
000 not everyone is making that profit
because part of it is their
it's the investment right they're going
to sell it off eventually and get that
money
and so they're not necessarily making a
profit off the rent itself
or they they own like this in vancouver
there's a lot of laneway houses
because it's something you can kind of
build on your property and rent out
and they're expensive like they're tiny
homes really that are
physically cemented to the ground and
they're just as expensive as
anything else in vancouver i i would add
that we can't talk about economics
without talking about scarcity
and the folks that own this property can
create scarcity by either making things
less available or increasing the price
i'll give
one example i'll just keep this
anonymous
but um someone has a
rental property and so far nobody's
moved in
well they also have a full-time job the
the person who owns the property
they can set the price say
x amount so far no one's moved in
apparently no one can afford it but the
person also has a full-time job so they
say well i'm just gonna wait
the house can sit empty until someone
comes along who can afford it
or instead they could lower the price
where probably someone could move in
but because they're not the person is
not dependent on the income
to pay the taxes on the rental property
they can be like i'll just wait till
someone
uh comes along who can afford it and so
the house
sits empty uh and there is a scarcity
it's it's a fake scarcity
i guess i want to say a word in in favor
of the parasites
um
it feels to me like it's it's a spectrum
like i know people who are struggling
who
uh in jamaica where i was born in other
places who were
just try to do better for their family
by renting out a room or something like
that
you know holding down two jobs and then
maybe buying a property
to move out of a neighborhood so i think
it's a scale and it's and it's a
it's it's the thing we are trapped in
and are all propagating to some extent
and if it may be in the purchases you
make and the investments you make
you move from one area to another you're
you know you're taking
advantage of that same system but there
are
the mega predators not mega predator
they are
calling them predators or parasites
again they're just very good
at the game and they take it to such an
obscene level
you don't even recognize it as the same
thing that you're doing
and i think that we have to take some
kind of ownership of that
but if we change if we can change
what is seen as the benefit of that
so in the benefit what they're just
trying to do is try to
to to live their optimal life if we can
redefine what an optimal life
looks like then this no longer becomes
a thing to go after that's just
that was a great segway mark into what
we would love it to look like what does
that look like
500 years in the future however far in
the future you need it to be for it to
be plausible
what does shelter look like for you for
humanity
you don't need to start if you don't
want mark anyway
well i i think i would like
i would like to see will be for me if if
shelter were seen more as
a holistic thing so
it brought those things that are
really valuable like the billionaire who
who
marries a young woman to try and feel
validated and try and feel something so
he's given everything to earn those
billions and yet he marries this
young girl who he knows will take him
for
all his money why he's after that thing
that's really valuable that deep
connectedness that feeling wanted that
kind of
that goes beyond pleasure i think so
if if that were
kind of extracted out and and shown as
this thing that you can get by living in
a shared tiny house and
just a kind of a wonderful you take a
if we could demonstrate that right in
the middle of game a
where there is all these people living
in these tiny houses
who are healthy who are just
extremely productive who are welcoming
or able to take care of themselves
who have some of those same game a
skills you know like
fit able to defend themselves sharp and
that could become the thing of the
future
this is the thing to go after now not
this but
this
you you ended up saying not quite what i
thought you were gonna say when you
first started off
um i was i was thinking when you said
like um
more of a holistic thing i was thinking
something along the lines of
where it's more of an access thing right
and of course you don't want to be
moving house every week i don't i don't
mean that but
you know like everyone has a
and i know there's a lot of messiness
with this but just just stay with me
everyone has a house right and then
exchanges emerge
when you want to go on holiday you want
to go to the bahamas wherever and so you
get in touch with people who have houses
in bahamas and some of them will want to
come to your country you figure out a
way
to exchange your houses and you know
when you're bored of living in one place
i want to move to somewhere else
and so you know you get on an exchange
in that area and you find someone who
wants to move to your area and so on and
so on and so on and so the
the notion of ownership is is gone right
you no longer own your house in the
sense that it is an asset which you can
sell for money it
is an asset which you can exchange with
other people right and and
so but the starting point of that is
that there is always enough for everyone
right
there's not a game of musical chairs but
there's always people left out homeless
right there's not not that
but where there is a maybe a small
surplus right there's always a few
standing empties just to have spare
capacity kind of thing
but basically there is one house per
unit of demand right be it a family
being a person being a couple whatever
it is right there there is one
unit of accommodation and i don't mean
to sound like everyone lives in the same
square block either
and i get that it's messy because
there's different houses in different
places and there's going to be people
who want the same thing and yeah well i
get it's messy but
broadly speaking that's my ideal vision
of the future right where there's just
this
healthy moving around of people from
house to house to house with not any
real need to do anything other than
maintain
and update the existing stock you know
what i mean because the population i'm
assuming is
relatively static globally as well
anyway that's i think i think i've made
it made
um i i can go i
i appreciate that it was said
it's a messy conversation um i don't
think this
right now is uh the format it's not long
enough
to get into the messiness of the
conversation
so like with that being said because
we've got problems with
yeah i love this uh um
housing exchange sort of thing your
shelter exchange
um and and diminishing the idea of
ownership but we got problems with
who does the maintenance and
um who responsibility like so it's
it's i want these rights but
rights have to come with
responsibilities and so
that's messy and that's it's an hour
long it's a much longer conversation
um i would like to have the conversation
about how many oh uh how many homes a
person
can own um this is
uh a conversation that you can't
normally have
but should one person be able to own
more than one home
should one person be able to own more
than three homes
um this is uh
i think
we could have laws about this um how
many homes
um an individual can own i think it's
part of the
problem so therefore what do i dream
that it's like
i haven't fully had that conversation
but i could imagine having a law
about how many homes a person is allowed
to own
i think that would help things a lot um
and lastly i guess just
i think that shelter should be a
tool for human flourishing
um if you go to
if you go to burning man it will change
your perception on like what is the
purpose of shelter
um it becomes less aesthetic and more
um more utilitarian
well we need to block ourselves from
these elements
um and when you get down to that level
then i think you understand the purpose
of communal
spaces more like okay so i need a place
to rest my head and like a quiet place
to study
the library kind of thing but then these
other spaces are like
communal spaces um and we should have
more of that uh more communal spaces
uh that would be very good if you ask me
thanks daniel do you want to share yours
carrie i know yeah it's just um
i think um in my perfect beautiful world
for shelter
you'd be able to buy your own but you'd
be made to live in it you wouldn't be
allowed to buy one unless you were
living
in it right so no no rent it out for
money but
there was also be places available for
people who don't want to live on the
road
or who aren't capable of living on their
own so there'd be like a
kind of like communal family set up
where you know people who didn't want to
live on their own could live in a place
and there'd be sort of a block there but
also the the the be socializing
um affordable prices not like the
so-called affordable prices
that then people can actually rent now
you know i mean
um because you know they saved the
social housing yet to get thrown up and
they're like you know
you can buy it for 600 000 pounds and i
don't know anyone who's in and that you
know what i mean but even just so they
um to pay that out there's mortgage and
that but i think you you need to have
options you need to have options whether
to rent
or to or to buy and if you're gonna buy
you need to live in it
right and i think that that would be
make that um
and anybody who's got more than one
who's not living in the other two
unless they rent them out under so like
um normal circumstances with normal
decent rents that people can actually
afford
then they take it off them
take it off them and develop social more
social stuff and then that'll like
sort it out you know i mean that was
sort of the red seeking
um and as said daniel said with the
communal and having communal spaces as
well
you need that as well um because there's
no there's no places to go
um anyway so that's what i think i would
like in a beautiful world
you know options and choices
and decent men all right let's share my
vision for
shelter and although i distinctly at the
beginning said we're talking about
shelter and not community
they're deeply tied together like i
don't want just a house with neighbors i
don't like
i want to have shelter that i
feel safe in that isn't moldy that isn't
um going to kill me that if i'm living
in an ideal future
self cleans itself has a lot of
technology that like knows what's going
on knows what mold is there knows when
there's a leak
but maintains that self too so not to
like worry about that
um that there's choice that i can
build my own house even though i have no
knowledge in that besides basic tool
working
that i can work with a group of people
to do it ourselves that we can
um find whether it's a small house and i
can find a community to just park it in
that i resonate with
or we're gonna build from the ground up
and build an apartment building that
when
you're you have access to shelter do you
want to live on your own or do you want
to live with other people
because the consent there is big right i
love what kerry said
like if you want to live with other
people or can't live by yourself that
you can
do you want to have a roommate right and
when there's no longer a need to have a
roommate for financial reasons then
you're going to be a better roommate
when you have one and going to be more
compatible to have the
tools to be able to find that
compatibility whether in community or in
roommates
to have help decorating my house i've
lived here for 10 years and my place is
just not beautiful because it's not my
skill set
but i would love to live in a beautiful
house i think my daughter would like to
live in a beautiful house
i'm waiting for her to get old enough to
decorate it to be the interior
designer um i like having the same house
i moved around a lot as a kid i've lived
in this house for
almost nine years it's the longest i've
lived anywhere and with that comes a lot
of stuff which i don't necessarily need
but to be able to have the ability i
love what eric said to be able to trade
and travel around the world and
um i don't know if i actually want that
but i want
other people to have access to that and
to be able to have choice
and see what kind of building materials
last
long enough to be able to share in the
labor so i don't have to pay someone you
know 10 people 30
an hour when they're not even making 30
an hour a lot of times they're making
less than minimum wage
working in extended families here in
vancouver i want to know
in when there's develop housing
development in vancouver especially
that it's not for profit that it's not a
housing product like that's being built
and has 30
profit i want them all to be co-housing
co-ops or owned by the city and we rent
them out or even at market
to be able to see to see that and we've
gone over the
the time for this but we can switch over
into
what we could do what would be the most
powerful thing we could do to empower
people to get shelter now right like
can't necessarily live in that ideal
world yet um with ten thousand people
and a hundred thousand dollars
i'll go if i had ten thousand people and
a hundred thousand dollars
i'd invest and i'd actually buy a place
and start that off so anybody who didn't
have anywhere to stay could actually
come so it'd be a bit like a hostel
a bit like a bed and breakfast but it'd
be up to you know i mean it wouldn't
just be about
oh you just come and stay here and then
that's what we're gonna do and then
you've got no network of people but if
you're about open them but
then from that i would probably end up
buying
more of them so they'll be so once
people got used to source like on their
feet and and
used to live in in place and that and
then
so they hopefully invest in another one
and give that and fight because you'd
find out whether
they want to live on their own or that
you know happy living with so like so
once that house got full i'd get another
one
and just you know leave the people with
if they would happy there then they
wanted to stay
leave them there and then buy another
one and do the same again
so you'd you'd have people who were
actually living in the properties
um in a way that they wanted to and
a rent and help getting the help that
they could so
that would be all tied in with that and
then so yeah so there would be a string
of them but
but give them the option to buy so like
once say once you've bought a place and
people want to stay there
and live there and if they get on their
feet and get jobs and stuff and if they
wanted the option to buy it i'd write
that in so they could buy a plate for
themselves
um and maybe so they'd get them to leave
it
back to a pot so i don't know whether
you'd have to set it up as a trust so
to make sure that nobody could come in
and change the rules of the game
and saying well you know you can sell
this and make all the money and run off
with the money so i think
i think that's what i'd do if i had that
yeah thanks carrie
i mean ten thousand people a hundred
thousand dollars that's ten dollars each
right so either putting it in
um you're not going to get ten thousand
people shelter for ten dollars each
but if there was a
website i could go to and get help
building a tiny house
get help um buying the materials in bulk
so that
it's not going to cost 40 60 000 to just
even build it myself
that we can share in the labor like barn
raisings um
possibly have a plot of and then find
plots of land right that people can
rent or kind of like trailer parks but
you know guppified
finding uh just comparing comparing
building materials or cobb houses the
best or yurts or like
being able to buy and sell used ones
so that people know that that
resource is available would be something
that i could see as a powerful
solution for for me anyway
i think the best thing you could do i
like a lot of what carrie said
i'm this is a really difficult
uh problem for me to come up with
solutions about
but i think if you went very practical
like like you're saying ten dollars a
person
i think you could
you could buy maybe some kind of
could buy a house and run it as a
non-profit
like 10 000 people together could buy a
house and
and run it as a non-profit to rent
out to people where maybe you have some
kind of model where you're just
trying to cover taxes um
what would that be a affordable housing
nonprofit
i guess that's the best i can come up
with
so the 10 000 people are essentially
making an altruistic investment in order
to help a handful of people
at the yeah fair enough fair enough
yeah that's that's hard it's only 10
bucks right i mean if you can actually
help say
12 people right by each putting 10 bucks
in a meaningfully and long term help
12 people i mean that's that's not a bad
return for your 10 bucks you know what i
mean it's really not bad
yeah i mean maybe you get like you know
blog updates of
you know who's living there and how
their life is going or something
yeah whatever no but as i said it's
really not bad
it's hard at this scale i mean i'm i'm
stymied at this scale this seems a
really hard thing to make any kind of a
bite in
sorry i i didn't mean to i didn't mean
to interrupt me mark go ahead well no if
you're on a roller
no no not at all not at all that's what
i mean i apologize for interrupting you
i i i was trying to just um
rock my brain and i the thing i came up
with
was similar to daniel's in in that
you provide a way
to um to do one project and i guess
if you had a if you had a hundred
thousand dollars again
like you would say eric you presented to
this 10 000 people here's a way
but i don't see it as altruistic here's
a way to tilt the world in a better
place to get the world you want
right so a hundred thousand dollars with
that
um and with as a non-profit making an
investment
you could possibly buy some land and um
borrow some money to do a small scale
group of tiny homes you know that are
connected in in some some kind of
community
uh holistically looking at
the
communal well-being spiritual well-being
physical well-being
and and you
you can track it as eric said just take
a look or
danielle mentioned this to you you're
involved you're personally invested in
and hopefully it it catches on you know
and so it's again i'm much more in favor
of
here's what works and it's i don't
want to send the the stormtroopers to
your house to take that house away from
you
i think government is just really really
bad at that kind of stuff it's just
it goes like who where do you draw the
line
who's who says that somebody's too rich
and if if if i go and enable those
people
enable those those those forces to say
this is the line
who's to say somebody will come after me
and say no that's
that line won't work this this is the
lie and you now have too much
so we're going to take that from you i
think
there's a danger in that and if we could
if we could say
that this is really a good way to live
and look look at look at this community
and look at how it's flourishing
you know don't you want to become part
of that and so i think
10 000 people could kind of get that
going in my mind anyways
i have a solution that's coming up um
you guys familiar with habitat for
humanity
and how their business model or what
we'll call the business model works
they what it is i don't know the
business
model like the people who get the house
they put in enough time
they are putting in sweat equity and i
think when they get the house they
either don't have a mortgage on it or
it's a low enough mortgage that they can
cover it
um because the community builds it with
them right and so you have to put in
doing something
like that but not for people who are
necessarily low income
um of all income levels and saying right
with 10 000 people we want to house 10
000 people eventually
but you don't necessarily know where on
that you're gonna fall um and you're
putting
in ten dollars for the material my guess
is you could build it two or three tiny
houses for a hundred thousand dollars
and um and then the people living in
there are paying
rent to the you know like they're
effectively paying a mortgage back to
the pool
in order to be able to buy the material
to build the nest but the labor and the
ingenuity and like the information's fed
back into the system so that every like
if you get a house in the beginning yay
but it's not going to be as good as
later
yeah all the 10
000 people that signed up for this
they'd be putting like a lottery
like you kind of just be waiting until
your number came up like oh i guess
we're moving into the tiny house village
and the people that were there at the
beginning
are paying for the next three houses and
then the next three houses
and it would it would be an
exponentially growing thing right
because the more houses you have people
paying rent the faster the next lot of
houses can be built right so
it's very slow to get going as you say
you're only doing three or four at a
time to start with
but once you've got 20 or 30 now you're
doing a dozen at a time and then when
you've got 50 you're doing 30 at a time
when you've got 100 you're doing 50 at a
time and
and so on and so on right it it all
expands very rapidly but
it's a really good idea it's a really
good idea and with a little bit of
clever finance
i mean i don't know a great deal about
this a little bit of clever finance once
you've got
a solid guaranteed monthly
amount of money going into a pool that
can provide a guarantee
for a loan which could then accelerate
the process further right you could
actually get upfront capital
to build houses before you'd accumulated
enough from contributions if you wanted
to get into all of that i mean there's
risk obviously
and this is one of those projects it's a
really cool idea i love it it's really
good
it's really good and it also very
quickly expands beyond the 10
000 right i mean once this has got a few
hundred people it now becomes a thing an
actual substantial thing generating
a substantial amount of monthly revenue
and it becomes an attractor now right it
would
that's it's a that's a fucking awesome
like housing which i was going to say in
the beginning is resources
labor and land right so if we're both
buying resources and doing it ethically
you know i mean like
however that looks that the land can be
done on an
if a farmer wants can offer a spot for
five places to park right or somebody
with rural lands
and then it doesn't work out and you can
find so you can find land pretty easy
you can use resources and we're sharing
in labor
right for things like electricians and
plumbers i guarantee you in that ten
thousand you have someone
that has that but even if you don't
those are the ones you're paying for the
labor
and everyone else is like that's habitat
for humanity you don't have to be
a skilled laborer you can just go and
volunteer and in that
you know like you maybe you're
volunteering two weeks out of the year
to go
and live in a tiny house and build more
tiny houses or whatever this looks like
i mean i would love to participate in
that
kind of reminds me of uh and if there's
like a housing exchange
um there i've never stayed at one of
these but there's a
group of campsites in the us i don't
know if they're international called
koa and like you can
go camping like if you're not a member
you can still roll up and say like hey i
need a campsite for the night
but you can become a member of koa camp
sites and they've got
campsites all over the u.s and you're
kind of part of this
koa campsite network um
i mean i don't know much about it beyond
that but i could see
okay so land is scarce and so if this
thing
were to multiply and build you'd the
non-profit
or whatever organization was running
this they'd be like okay so
we have you know some land over here
some land in this country some land in
this country and like
maybe you have some fluidity where
once you were in one of the houses you
almost have like a six month or twelve
year
like a time share sort of similar to a
timeshare sort of community right where
you're all moving around within each
other's
property pool yeah so yeah all of that
coming back it's a really cool idea
it's got real potential
so what you have to do is like look at
what are the ways this could fail
i guess what are the downsides well i i
straight away can see a couple right
logistically it's very tricky you've got
000 people in the early stages anyway
you've got 10 000 people contributing
their manpower and expertise and
whatever it's the building of three
houses right you can't have all 10 000
of them
clustering around three houses right so
the
fair distribution of you know making
sure that everybody
does their bit in the whole process of
getting 10 000 homes built right that's
very very tricky to keep track of and
i'm not saying that everyone must
expend exactly the same number of jewels
of energy in their contribution i don't
mean that but
but just that some
some method of anti-defect because it
would be quite easy i think in a pool of
10 000 people it would be quite easy to
sit there and be invisible and not do
anything and end up getting your house
built for you the only one you actually
contributed to was your one you know
what i mean i think it'd be quite easy
for people to disappear into that kind
of thing if
so yeah that's that's one thing so
habitat for humanity and i'm i'm
people you put in sweat equity right so
you don't get your house until you've
built four right like you don't get your
house until you've equivalently built
four or something along those lines
right like there's not
and so and or did you make a commitment
to build to be involved in four other
builds afterwards even though you've got
the first
yeah right and most people involved in
habitat for humanity are never getting a
house right they're there because they
want to give someone else a house
they're there because they want to give
that labor
and that might be the point right and if
you're giving 10 a month and you never
build a house and you never get a house
you're still helping other people get
houses and that might be
enough of an incentive and then you
never have to go and build it if it's
enjoyable to go build it like if i think
about abundance farm
which is a farm here that you can it's
it's a community owned actually no sir
it's not community owned but it's
kind of kind of community owned and you
go and participate in the labor and you
get food out of it right so
instead of going and paying people
minimum wage to pick food they're
collectively using their labor and it's
fun to go there it's a community event
it's not
did you how many strawberries per hour
did you pick right and they're eating
together and singing together
that's part of it like building together
is fun if it's not
you know like for profit gotta get
enough out like you wanna get them out
you wanna be efficient you also wanna
make the next ones better and buy stuff
in bulk so it's cheaper and make sure
it's efficient and and
there's so many places to do the work
that
they're even like with the pareto
distribution
eighty percent will do twenty twenty
percent will do eighty percent of the
work
hopefully they get their houses first
but yeah
we need to have to say there's
some spectrum of merit
based on participation uh
and maybe it's not
one to one um because then you kind of
then it gets competitive
also in the game b space
how do you make it omni win how do you
make it win win
um and not rival risk if it was a one to
one
whoever puts in the most hours gets the
house first
i mean then you have what you have like
this rush of people putting in hours
some people then you know we're trying
to combat
bad luck so some folks
you need of some mix of lottery
and participation maybe
i like what jubilee said cultivating
that feeling of we're doing it because
it's
fun right we're doing it because we want
other people to get houses right we're
not doing it for ourselves
we're doing it primarily to make houses
for other people that need them right
and if at some point along the road i
get one myself then so much the best but
actually
that's so cut some finding ways to
cultivate that spirit
feels feels like the right feels like
the right
ratio or you say you know for the first
10 houses are only for other people
and then after that then we build one
for one of us
uh or you have a ratio that's like two
to one
for every two houses we make for other
folks
then there's one for us i don't know
just throwing
ideas out there yeah i mean i some some
i do think some kind of merit
recognition of contribution kind of
thing i thought
without getting all gestapo about it and
and
you know encouraging lots of virtue
signaling and all that i do think some
kind of recognition
of level of contribution i don't know
it's very it becomes very tricky very
quickly i want to let mark speak because
he was just about to and i know he's not
his he's not as big as interrupting
people as the rest of us
so and then yeah not as big an
interruption
he doesn't interrupt people we do well i
like to listen to a lot
uh it's i i think it's a combination of
what jubilee said and what daniel said
it's it's it's there's a lot of that
happens organically but there
there is a big plus to be said for
doing something to tilt the world in the
right direction and if that
was the biggest piece like providing
homes for people who can't afford them
it gives people hope
and takes them off the street you don't
have six cops
going to a cost one homeless guy like i
saw i've seen happen in saskatoon
but two cop cars and one uh emergency
vehicle
for one homeless guy you know uh and if
you provide homes first
get those people off the street it saves
you money so even
the the person the most conservative
person can see
that there's something to that right
so it's it's something that is a win-win
for everyone to provide homes and maybe
that's the thing daniel
is provide homes for the homeless first
and then after that um
possibly i i don't know but i there is a
big thing to providing homes
that are not for you because it tilts
the world in a better
better direction absolutely the other
thing that was coming up was the exact
opposite
that the first people let's say there's
10 people who have the skills to build
their own house
and they do it in a way where they're
offering that knowledge to everybody
else and so they get
like 100 000 goes to their material
they're
showcasing it in like a youtube video
type way so that people
can can follow along but they're also so
now they have their little tiny village
they don't have to pay rent and they can
focus on using these skills to
to um have teams to build more and more
right like
the people who have the highest skills
to give
in this area get their houses so they
don't have to worry about that stress
and then they get to build because it's
going to be something that they're
passionate about if it's something they
like to do right and they
continually build the houses um and i
also like what you
said about yes building them for people
who like the homeless and people who
don't who aren't necessarily gonna have
it and then figuring out how to build
them for ourselves
within that yeah it's a big difference
between building
different houses for people that already
have houses and building houses people
that don't have houses that are there
yeah there is a big difference between
those two things
but just even having a community of
people to
like if i i'm not one of those 10 people
i don't have again the skill but if i
was one of them
you know like then i don't have to i
just have to work the buzz saw i just
have to
pound the nails in like it isn't i just
have to follow a direction
i don't necessarily have to have all of
that information and that i love that i
want to be the sous chef not the
person in charge in things like manual
labor
that's what i enjoy i would think that
it's important to recognize that there's
value think of the people volunteering
for habitat for humanity
even if they never get a house they're
gaining valuable skills and they're
learning valuable things
so emphasizing that hey if you have
never
done plumbing before there's an
opportunity
to learn this and you just gain the
skill
uh and you can take that with you
there you go there's your omni win
scenario right everybody definitely wins
right
you've made it i've rent i rented my
whole life
um there's things i've asked my landlord
i can't do things on the house they have
interesting perceptions about um
insurance or what would happen if
something goes wrong
i can't do upgrades i can't learn
how to do plumbing on this house if
something breaks
they have to do it where do i i mean
sure i guess there's
places to go to learn it but i'm just
saying that's valuable
um so we're getting down to the hour i
would like to go around and share what
we think is the most powerful
thing that we could do with ten thousand
people and a hundred thousand dollars
that we discussed or comes up in the
moment
and then we will stop the recording and
you all can continue the conversation if
you would like well
i go prepare for my next conversation
for the day
i said exasperate i'm super excited
about my next conversation for the day
well i'll i'll go um i just have two
things
one i think that it's normal i've been
in organizations
that count volunteer hours um
and so for events yeah if you've
volunteered you count the volunteer
hours and you get a discount
uh on your ticket or if you do enough
you could get a free ticket to the next
event so i think it's normal to count
volunteer hours that could be applicable
to this idea and i guess
i love the second thing is i love the
idea of like keeping a mission in mind
you know what if the overall mission was
like do this project and then
for every 10 houses the group built for
itself it also built
a house for outside the group
for homeless or something and so you
keep this ratio
um and i think that keeping like a
mission
in mind would keep things
on the right track
right there with silence for a few
seconds so i will share mine i do think
um having
the habitat for humanity people putting
in 10 a month
and then we start building them and
showcase that in a transparent
fun way so that people can feel like
they're participating in it
and make sure it's clear that you're
doing this out of
that same habitat for humanity feeling
and if you get a house out of it awesome
and that was the other that the people
who get the first houses if they're part
of the same village are people who are
willing to share the knowledge but also
the
the transparency that no one else should
have to do like doing it on video right
sharing like hey here's what we learned
and here's what it looks like to live
here
those people are more willing to do that
kind of thing so that
because it's going to bring more media
attention more stuff to get more people
to get more money to get
the next ones built yeah i like the
habitat for humanity i did as well
so i'd say i'd say that um that was a
good idea
yeah i think that's that's a good idea
too as well um
and just the feeling that it's
it's enlightened self-interest
to do this um show a better way and to
do something have that mission to do do
something for the wholeness as well
i think that's kills the world in a
better direction
so i'm gonna win
as you spoke that's the first time i've
heard the jamaican in you up until now
i've only sort of heard an american
accent it's the first time i've heard
the jamaican in here
canadian eric what did you share yet
what do you think the most powerful
no but i think it's clear what i think i
mean i was all over while we were
talking so i think it's pretty clear
what i think
all right so just to have it at the end
and i just wanted to add even though i
already shared mine
then when carrie shared um
what i think would be even more powerful
what daniel added that we build 10 and
we build an extra one
that extra one going to a community
that's like the phoenix lighthouse
i think would be the most powerful come
be part of this you don't have to have
your
shit together yet this is a place for
you to find yourself this is a place for
you to heal
would be so amazing so that would be
even more powerful
all right so i'm going to stop the
recording and then
you guys can talk